Howell, George Papers on Microfilm 5423 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
George Howell Papers on Microfilm
1864-1910
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Howell, George
5423 mf
2.78 cubic feet
25 microfilm reels
Papers (documents), microfilm.
Autobiography, diaries, and correspondence of George Howell; also included are minutes of the IWMA, papers of the Trades Union Congress, and news clippings.
5649076
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, May 13, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 12, 2019
Biographical / Historical
George Howell was born in Wrington, Somerset, the oldest of eight children of a builder and contractor. During the week he worked twelve hours a day as a mortar-boy, and at one point he was a bricklayer, but, dedicated his Sundays to reading.
Howell didn't enjoy working as a builder so he got a job as an apprentice shoemaker. While working at this he was introduced to radical newspapers including the Northern Star and the Red Republican. As a result he joined the Chartist movement in 1848.
Howell relocated to London in 1854 where he returned to bricklaying, because he was unable to find work as a shoemaker. He continued to attend radical political meetings and through these meetings he met several prominent people, including Karl Marx, George Holyoake, Charles Bradlaugh and Frederic Harrison. Howell joined the Operative Bricklayers' Society (a New Model Trade Union) in 1859, and was a major part in leading a strike in support of a nine-hour working day. Because of his work with the union he became one of the foremost New Model unionists, along with Robert Applegarth and George Potter, but ended up blacklisted by employers for five years.
In 1861 he was elected, along with Potter and Applegarth to the executive of the London Trades Council (LTC). He also became full-time secretary of the Reform League in 1865 after a campaign for universal suffrage. Howell organised demonstrations in London in 1866 and 1867, and was a big influence on the campaign behind the 1867 Reform Act. Even with all of this, he was still not happy with the scale of reform and continued to campaign for universal suffrage.
Howell was appointed secretary of the Trades Union Congress (TUC) in 1871, and was a regular contributor to the journal the Bee-Hive and published several books in the 1870s.
He tried unsuccessfully to become a part of parliament at Aylesbury in the general elections of 1868 and 1874 and at Stafford in a by- election in 1881. Howell was finally successful in 1885 as Lib-Lab candidate for Bethnal Green North East, London. He helped to pass the Merchant Shipping Act 1894, while in Parliament, and was successful in defending his seat in 1886 and 1892, but, lost his seat in 1895 to the Conservative Mancherjee Bhownagree.
Due to poor health he retired from public life. His old friend Robert Applegarth and the TUC raised a 1650 testimonial to buy him an annuity before his death in 1911.
Scope and Contents
Autobiography, diaries, and correspondence of George Howell; also included are minutes of the IWMA, papers of the Trades Union Congress, and news clippings. Papers are noteworthy relative to American radicalism because of his work as Council of the International Workingmen's Association and his association with prominent American leaders. Originals at the Bishopgate Institute in London. Materials were filmed on behalf of the Society for the Study of Labour and Radical History.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Howell, George, 1833-1910
5649076
- Autobiography - Part I - Vol. 1-6 (Reel 1)
  Scope and Contents
  positive
- Autobiography - Part I - vol. 6 continued (Reel 2)
- IWMA Minutes - 1866-1869: Part 2 (Reel 3)
- Reform League Papers - Part 3 (Reel 4)
- Reform League Papers - Part 3 Cont. (Reel 5)
- TUC Parliamentary Committee Papers - Part 4 (Reel 6)
- Plimsoll Papers - Part 5 (Reel 7)
- Part 5 cont.; Part 6 & items missing (Reel 8)
- Personal Diaries 1864-1908 - Part 8 (Reel 9)
- Personal Diaries 1864-1908 - Part 8 (Reel 10)
- Letter Books (1883-1884, 1865-1879) - Part 9 (Reel 11)
- Letter Books - Part 9 cont. (Reel 12)
- Part 9 cont. - Letter books (Reel 13)
- Part 9 cont. Letter books (Reel 14)
- Part 9 cont. - Letter books (Reel 15)
- Part 9 cont. - Letter books (Reel 16)
- Part 9 cont. - Letter books (Reel 17)
- Part 9 cont. - Letter books (Reel 18)
- Part 9 cont. - Letter books (Reel 19)
- Index to Howell's correspondence with the correspondence 1867-1906: Part 10 (Reel 20)
- Part 10 cont. - Correspondence (Reel 21)
- Part 10 cont. - Correspondence (Reel 22)
- Part 10 cont. - Correspondence (Reel 23)
- Part 11 - Industrial Notes Engineering, 1909-1910 (Reel 24)
- Part 12 - News Cuttings (Reel 25)